Okay בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף Daf is ע"א, Ayin Aleph,
זבחים Zevachim 71, and we start a new פרק. Perek. If you're
we are at the very bottom of ע עמוד ב, Ayin Amud
Bet, the פרק Perek is called כל הזבחים, Kol HaZevachim, and as
we'll see, we're really moving beyond here the details of how the
קרבנות Korbanot are brought and dealing with some broader issues, specifically the
issues of תערובת. Ta'arovet. What happens when one thing gets mixed up
with others? And this is a topic that comes up in many
different contexts. One location is חולין, Chullin, talking about בשר בחלב, Basar
BeChalav, talking about גיד הנשה, Gid HaNasheh, certain things that are forbidden
to be eaten like in various ways. There's it comes up in
זרעים, Zeraim, dealing with כלאיים Kilayim and ערלה, Orlah, and it comes
up here in קדשים Kodashim as well. So the tenor of the
discussion and the nature of the things we're discussing is going to
be quite different. Also if your eyes glance over, you will see
that it's a very
short
עמוד א. Amud Aleph. There's some very large תוספות Tosafot in here,
some that are directly relevant to our סוגיא Sugya and some that
are talking about much broader issues. So I will try to distill
the ones that are relevant to our סוגיא, Sugya, but it will
be a short דף Daf today. Okay, so let's take a look.
Bottom of ע עמוד ב. Ayin Amud Bet. כל הזבחים שנתערבו בחטאת
המיתות. Kol HaZevachim Shenitarvu BeChatat HaMetot. All of the קרבנות, Korbanot, you
know animal קרבנות, Korbanot, that got mixed up with a חטאת Chatat
that has to die. There are five type of חטאות Chataot that
are that you that if that you can't redeem them and you
would have to let them die. What are they? It's the mnemonic
ותמנ"ע. Vitamna. So ו Vav is ולד חטאת. Vlat Chatat. If a
חטאת Chatat if a חטאת Chatat is female, if it has a
child, so that has a all of them are because they sort
of have a status of a חטאת, Chatat, but a חטאת Chatat
is for a חטא Chet and these are ones that are lacking
any חטא Chet but they just have that status. So that sort
of is the conceptual group here. So something that is born of
a חטאת, Chatat, ולד חטאת. Vlat Chatat. תמורת חטאת, Tmurat Chatat, if
somebody tries to say זו תמורה זו, Zu Tmura Zu, exchange it,
which doesn't work, and both are קדוש, Kadosh, but the one that
is the תמורה Tmura cannot be offered up.
מ Mem is מתו בעליה. Metu Ba'aleha. The owners died. So now
it was for a חטא, Chet, but it's not meaningful to bring
it because the owners are already dead.
נ Nun is נתכפרו באחר Niskapru Ba'acher that you know the owners
set aside a חטאת Chatat and then it got lost, so they
found another it so they used another animal for the חטאת Chatat
and now it was atoned for. And now they found the one
that was originally had been the sanctified. So it's for a חטא
Chet and it's for these owners, but it's no longer usable because
the thing for that חטא Chet was already brought. And ע Ayin
is עברה שנתה. Avra Shnatah. It's no longer one year old. So
a חטאת Chatat that falls into any of those five categories, the
הלכה Halacha is that you have to let it die. All other
קרבנות Korbanot if they can't be used, you let them get a
מום Mum and you redeem them, but the הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha
LeMoshe MiSinai is here that you let it die. Okay, so you
now have this now it sounds like you have one קרבן Korban
that got mixed up in a flock of חטאות המיתות, Chataot HaMetot,
but the
גמרא Gemara clarifies and it does not mean that it means you
have a flock of קרבנות Korbanot and you have one חטאת המיתות
Chatat HaMetot that gets mixed up in it. So you have a
hundred חטאות Chataot ready to be brought and one חטאת המיתות Chatat
HaMetot gets mixed up. Okay, so you can't now if you bring
all of them you'll definitely have been bringing one invalid קרבן. Korban.
או בשור הנסקל, O BeShor HaNiskal, or an ox that had gored
somebody and therefore was going to be stoned,
had gored and killed somebody. So that gets mixed up. אפילו אחת
בריבוא, Afilu Achat Beribo, even if it is this one forbidden animal
getting mixed up with 10,000 kosher animals, ימותו כולם. Yamutu Kulam. You
have to let all of them die. The same way the שור
הנסקל Shor HaNiskal would die or the חטאת המיתות Chatat HaMetot would
die, so you have to let all of these die as well.
Okay, now what you might be thinking here is well one minute
I get that well there's a couple of points that are being
made here. Number one is that we don't say ביטול. Bitul. Okay
normally one thing gets mixed up with others we would say ביטול.
Bitul. Here we don't say ביטול, Bitul, the גמרא Gemara will discuss
why not but not to ruin the secret at least the answer
the גמרא Gemara settles on is because they're live animals, בעלי חיים,
Ba'alei Chaim, and each one is important by itself and therefore there's
no ביטול. Bitul. Okay, so there's no ביטול, Bitul, so you can't
bring any individual one because it might be the אסור Assur one.
But why don't you wait till they all get a blemish and
then you redeem it on money and then you use that money
to go ahead and to buy you know other קרבנות Korbanot
and then you can go ahead and benefit from all of the
remaining animals that are now חולין? Chullin? But the answer is you
can't because the same way you can't use a חטאת המיתות Chatat
HaMetot as a קרבן, Korban, you can't use a חטאת המיתות Chatat
HaMetot to benefit from it. The same way you can't use a
שור הנסקל Shor HaNiskal as a קרבן, Korban, you can't benefit from
a שור הנסקל. Shor HaNiskal. So even if you redeemed all of
them, there's nothing here that can be used. It can't be used
for the מזבח Mizbe'ach in the הקדש Hekdesh state because you might
be offering the שור הנסקל. Shor HaNiskal. It can't be benefited from
from you know in a non-הקדש Hekdesh state if you were to
redeem it because also you can't benefit from a חטאת המיתות, Chatat
HaMetot, you can't benefit from a שור הנסקל, Shor HaNiskal, and any
one
particular... Now let's say it was different. The thing that got mixed
up with the קרבנות Korbanos was not something— was something that could
not be brought as a קרבן, Korban, but could be benefit— but
could, you know, have a layperson benefit from it. For example. Okay,
שור שנעבדה בו עבירה, Shor She'Ne'evda Bo Aveira, an ox that, you
know, any— that a sin was done to it. What type of
sin? So the משנה Mishna explains.
או— O now this או O is sort of like רש"י Rashi
says: colon, for example, here's the examples of נעבדה בו עבירה. Ne'evda
Bo Aveira. שהמית את האדם על פי עד אחד. She'Heimis Es Ha'Adam
Al Pi Ed Echad. It would have been a שור הנסקל, Shor
HaNiskal, it killed somebody, but there was only one witness not two
witnesses. Okay? So in that case the הלכה Halacha is that it
cannot be brought as a קרבן, Korban, but it can be— a
layperson can benefit from it, there's no איסור Issur because you don't
have to stone it, but it's still invalid for a קרבן. Korban.
או
על פי הבעלים, O Al Pi Ha'Ba'alim, or the owners admit that
it— that it gored. Okay? The הלכה Halacha is you only stone
a שור הנסקל Shor HaNiskal כמיתת הבעלים כך מיתת השור Ke'Misas Ha'Ba'alim
Kach Misas Ha'Shor if there are two witnesses. Okay? But with one
witness we learn out that there still is an איסור— Issur or—
for the מזבח, Mizbe'ach, to bring it as a sacrifice. ברובע ונרבע,
Be'Rove'a Ve'Nirva, or an animal that was used in an act of
bestiality, whether a female that— that,
you know, whether female animal, male animal, you know, with the counterpart
of the human, it was used for an act of bestiality, so
that also, if there were two witnesses, it would be forbidden in
benefit, that's actually not explicit here in this משנה, Mishna, but it's
based on some other רש"י, Rashi, תוספות, Tosafos, other גמרא. Gemara. If
there were two— and not exactly clear where we know it from
the פסוקים Pesukim either, but— but the assumption here is that if
it were two witnesses it would be forbidden for a layperson to
benefit, but if it's only one witness or the owner who— who
says that this happened, it's permissible for benefit for a layperson but
cannot be used for the מזבח. Mizbe'ach. Okay,
במוקצה, Be'Muktzeh, something not מוקצה Muktzeh on שבת, Shabbos, set aside for,
you know, עבודה זרה, Avoda Zara, ונעבד, Ve'Ne'evad, something actually worshipped as
עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara. Surprisingly that does not become אסור Assur for
a layperson because even though things worshipped as עבודה זרה Avoda Zara
are איסורי הנאה, Issurei Hana'ah, that's only when they're inanimate objects. Live
things, animals, cannot become אסור בהנאה Assur Be'Hana'ah whether they're worshipped for
עבודה זרה, Avoda Zara, but they can become forbidden to be used
as a קרבן. Korban. Okay, באתנן ומחיר, Be'Esnan U'Mechier, a— something that
was given as a gift to a prostitute, a payment for a
prostitute, or something that was exchanged for a dog. All of these
things are specifically cannot be used for a קרבן Korban but can
be eaten and benefited by— by a layperson. בכלאים, Be'Kilayim, if it
is a— animal that was born of a hybrid, a crossbreed. Okay,
now that's pretty interesting because remember, this is getting mixed up with
kosher קרבנות, Korbanos, so it would have to be some type of
a crossbreed that you cannot tell by looking at it what its
parentage was. ובטרפה, U'Be'Treifa, an animal that was a טרפה, Treifa, also
the גמרא Gemara will have to figure out what the scenario is
that it could be a טרפה Treifa that you cannot visibly identify
it because it's getting mixed up with kosher animals. Okay, but the
טרפה Treifa also is going to be difficult because the טרפה Treifa
is the one thing that cannot be eaten by humans. So— we'll
get back to that in a minute. It can— you can use
a טרפה Treifa to, you know, for— to get benefit from, you
can use it for dog food, but you cannot eat it. All
right, so ביוצא דופן, Be'Yotze Dofen, or something that was a Cesarean
section. We learn from the פסוק Pasuk שור כשב או עז כי
יולד Shor Kesev O Ez Ki Yivaled that it has to be
born, you know, normally, not through a Cesarean section, and if so
it cannot be used as a קרבן. Korban. So all these things,
okay, one of them gets mixed up of any of these things
that can't be used for a קרבן Korban but are permissible at
least for a human— for a layperson to benefit from, gets mixed
up with these kosher קרבנות. Korbanos. So now we have a solution
what to do. You can't bring the קרבנות Korbanos because you— you'll
be bringing something that's a פסול Pasul קרבן. Korban. Okay, you know,
you can't say whichever one is not a קרבן Korban I'm מקדיש
Makdish it, I sanctify it, it's not going to help. It's invalid
as a קרבן. Korban. So number one, it's not בטל. Battel. Now
that it's not בטל, Battel, what can you do? You can't bring
everything as a קרבן, Korban, one of them cannot be a kosher
קרבן. Korban. So now though, because they can be benefited by laypeople,
there is a solution. So here's what you're going to do.
נתערבו חולין בתמימים
נתערבו בחולין— Nis'arvu Chullin Bi'Tmimim Nis'arvu Be'Chullin so if it— if—
I'm sorry, I skipped a line. Back to the top line of
the עמוד ב. Amud Beis. ירעו עד שיסתאבו, Yir'u Ad She'Yista'avu, you
let them graze until they— get a blemish. Okay, now that they
have a blemish, they can all be redeemed. So let's say you
have nine kosher, you know, עולות Olos and one got mixed up
here that is— like a Cesarean section or whatever it is, it
gets mixed up. So what are you going to do? You let
all ten animals graze till they all get a
blemish. וימכרו ויביא בדמי היפה שבהן מאותו המין. Ve'Yimachru Ve'Yavi Bi'Dmei Ha'Yafeh
She'Bahen Me'Oso Ha'Min. So now you go ahead and you sell them,
okay, and you can sell and in the act of selling them,
the קדושה Kedusha of the animal transfers to the money. So, you
know, so you don't know which one is a, you know, which
of which one is the problematic one. But it doesn't matter. You're
going to sell all ten of them, okay, the person who's buying
them can go ahead and eat them, שחט shecht them, whatever, once
the sale takes place, the קדושה Kedusha of the nine transfers to
the money that you were that, you know, that was paid for,
okay, and then this person can go ahead and eat them, right,
they're all kosher animals, their קדושה Kedusha has been removed, has been
transferred in the sale, so what if it's a Cesarean section or
a crossbreed or any of these things, they're not forbidden to be
eaten, we'll get back to the טרפה, traifa, he goes and he
benefits from them, the money he paid, you know, now you go
ahead that money has the קדושה, Kedusha, you go ahead and you
use that money to buy nine עולות olas and you bring nine
עולות, olas, okay, for the original owners and everybody is happy, so
that's what you do. All right, so now what does it mean
בדמי היפה שבהן? bidmei hayafe shebahen? Because let's imagine that, you know,
I don't know, let's say of the ten, one was worth a
hundred, one was worth ninety, eighty, seventy, sixty, fifty, all the way
down to ten dollars. Okay, does that work, whatever. Anyway, all the
way down to ten. So obviously, you know, you have to get
a scenario that's not that drastic because if it was that big
of a difference in value, you'd probably be able to identify which
one was the one that got mixed up. But anyway, so now
you're selling these ten animals.
Some of that money you can salvage for yourself. You don't even
have to use to bring an עולה. ola. Why not? Because one
of those animals wasn't קדוש. kadosh. So how much of the money
do you keep for yourself? So if every animal cost a hundred,
so then you use nine hundred so you sold the ten for
a thousand dollars. You bring nine hundred dollars to go ahead and
bring עולות olas and you bring nine עולות olas and buy them
for a hundred dollars, and the hundred dollars you pocket for yourself
because that's the cost of the animal that got mixed up and
that wasn't קדוש. kadosh. All right, if however, let's say they were
of different values, then you have to assume the higher value ones
were the הקדש. hekdesh. So in my scenario, this person paid you
the money for all these animals, you would have to assume the
only amount you could pocket for yourself is the cost of the
least expensive one, the ten dollar one. Okay, maybe that ten dollar
one was an עולה, ola, maybe the one that was actually, you
know, the Cesarean section that wasn't a קרבן korban was actually worth
ninety dollars, and you really should be able to pocket ninety dollars
for yourself, but because you don't know, you have to give the
benefit of the doubt to הקדש. hekdesh. All right, so you sell
so you use the more valuable ones to to assume that those
were the הקדש hekdesh ones and that's the money that now goes
to buying future עולות olas and
the money for the least valuable one is what you pocket for
yourself. So that is what it means יביא בדמי היפה שבהן מאותו
המין. yavi bidmei hayafe shebahen me'oso hamin. You bring from the same
type עולות, olas, you're going to use the money to bring עולות
olas of the same מין, min, does it mean cow or sheep,
it means same type of קרבן korban and you do it from
the ones that are the most expensive, you assume those were the
קרבנות. korbanot. All right, so that's what you do now that you
can derive benefits or you can salvage it through this, you know,
through this process. Now, what about the טרפה? traifa? If you're going
to sell these ten animals and there's a טרפה traifa mixed in
them, the owner can't use them for to eat. So how are
you going to salvage it? So it's true, he can't eat it,
but he can שחט shecht all of them and use it for
dog food. So instead of getting a hundred dollars for each one,
you might only get fifty dollars or ten dollars for each one,
okay, but you do the best you can and at least that's
what you salvage, but at least some type of a fix is
possible. Now,
נתערבו בחולין תמימים, nisarvu bechulin tmimim,
excuse me, let me do that again, נתערבו בחולין תמימים. nisarvu bechulin
tmimim. Let's say it was a mixture of non-sanctified and sanctified animals,
nothing problematic with the animal, okay, so nothing problematic, you just you
have here one עולה ola and one חולין chulin and you just
don't know which is which. ימכרו החולין לצורך אותו מין. Yimachru hachulin
l'tzorech oso min. That's an easy solution. You find somebody that needs
to bring an עולה ola and you say, hey you, I see
you need to bring an עולה, ola, one of these is is
ready to be sold as an עולה, ola, one is already an
עולה ola but one is ready to be sold as an עולה.
ola. Give me your money that you were looking to buy a
sheep for an עולה ola and we'll say the one here that's
right now not, you know, is still חולין, chulin, now that'll be
your עולה. ola. We'll give both to the כהנים kohanim to the,
you know, the כהן kohen and the כהן kohen will bring both
קרבנות. korbanot. The one that's yours will work for you and the
one that's Reuven's will work for him. The כהן kohen doesn't have
to have any particular owner in mind, it automatically works for him,
so we have amongst these two sheep Reuven's עולה ola and a
חולין, chulin, you need to bring an עולה, ola, so fine, pay
us the money and now both of them are עולה. ola. we
don't know which is which, but they're both עולה olahs and the
כהן Kohen will bring will offer both of them. So that's an
easy solution. קדשים בקדשים מין במינו. Kodshim bekodshim min bemino. Now let's
say what you got mixed up is you got mixed up קדשים
kodshim with other קדשים, kodshim, okay, like ראובן's Reuven's עולה olah and
שמעון's Shimon's עולה olah got mixed up. Well, I already sort of
told you the answer to that. What's the problem? זה יקרב לשם
מי שהוא וזה יקרב לשם מי שהוא. Ze yikarev leshem mi shehu
veze yikarev leshem mi shehu. You don't have to know who the
owner is, so you just bring the קרבנות korbanot and they work
for whoever they work for. Okay, so the חולין, chulin, חולין chulin
and קדשים kodshim really you get it into be a קדשים וקדשים
kodshim vekodshim case. That's easy. Now, קדשים בקדשים מין בשאינו מינו. Kodshim
bekodshim min beshe'eino mino. Let's say you have, you know, an עולה
olah and a שלמים shelamim get mixed up, right? שלמים shelamim can
be female. So an עולה olah and a שלמים shelamim get mixed
up, and you don't know which is which. So forget who the
owner is. The problem is how are you going to be מקריב
makriv them, right? The עולה olah you burn it, the שלמים shelamim
you eat it. Okay, and if it's a, you know, if it's
an עולה olah and a חטאת chatat it's even worse because what
you do with the blood is totally different. So how are you
supposed to solve this? Okay,
so what can you do right now? ירעו עד שיסתאבו, Yiru ad
sheyistavu, so let both of them graze until they get a מום.
mum. ויביא בדמי יפה שביניהן ממין
זה—we'll Veyavi bidmei yafeh shebeineihen mimiin ze take out the word וימכרו,
veyimachru, doesn't really matter—ויביא בדמי יפה שביניהן ממין זה ובדמי יפה שביניהן
ממין זה ויפסיד המותר מביתו. Veyavi bidmei yafeh shebeineihen mimiin ze uvidmei
yafeh shebeineihen mimiin ze veyafsid hamutar mibeito. So what you do is
let's say it is ראובן's Reuven's עולה olah and שמעון's Shimon's שלמים,
shelamim, okay?
So ראובן's Reuven's עולה olah and שמעון's Shimon's שלמים shelamim get mixed
up, you can't tell which is which. But you do know one
of them cost $100 and one cost $90. It's not clear, you
know, by looking at them which is which, but they do know
that they cost different—they don't remember whose is whose, whatever the case
is.
So you have to be concerned that each one might have had
the more expensive one. So here's what you
do: if you knew which was which and you just wanted to
get the קדושה kedushah away from the animals, you'd put $100 in
one pile, $90 in another and you'd say, you know, the עולה
olah which is 100 is transferred to this $100, the שלמים shelamim
which is 90 is transferred to this 90, use the 100 to
buy a substitute עולה olah and the 90 to buy a substitute
שלמים. shelamim. Okay, but of course if you knew which was which
you wouldn't have to do this. So now what we're going to
do is we're going to say whichever one is the עולה, olah,
we don't know which is the עולה olah which is the שלמים,
shelamim, we don't know which is worth $100 which is worth $90.
So you say whichever one is the עולה olah is transferred to
this $100, you have to say $100 because the עולה olah might
be the $100 one, and you use the $100 to go buy
a
שלמים shelamim and—to go buy an עולה, olah, excuse me, I don't
know where that came from. And then you say whichever one is
the שלמים shelamim is transferred to this $100, and you have to
say that because the שלמים shelamim might be worth $100, okay? And
then you use that $100 to buy a שלמים, shelamim, and now
you know those two animals are חולין chulin and you can go
ahead and eat them and benefit from them. So once they were
mixed up there was nothing you could do because you can't bring—which
is the עולה olah which is the שלמים shelamim you don't know
how to bring them, but by saying whichever is the עולה olah
is transferred to this pile of money and use this pile of
money to buy an עולה, olah, whichever is the שלמים shelamim is
transferred to this pile and use this pile of money to buy
שלמים, shelamim, now you can sort of, you know, unmix them up,
you can, you know, separate them out, as it were, bring an
עולה olah separately and a שלמים shelamim separately. But because you don't
know which was the more expensive, you're going to have to put
out an extra $10.
So you use the highest amount of money to buy for an
עולה olah and the highest amount of money to buy the שלמים,
shelamim, ויפסיד המותר מביתו, Veyafsid hamutar mibeito, and the rest has to
come out of pocket. נתערבו בבכור ובמעשר. Nitarvu bevochor uvima'aser.
Now let's say the עולה olah didn't get mixed up with a
שלמים, shelamim, the עולה olah got mixed up with בכור bechor and
מעשר. ma'aser. Now you got a problem because בכור bechor and מעשר
ma'aser you can't redeem.
So again you can't bring both because an עולה olah you burn
and the בכור bechor and מעשר ma'aser you eat, and בכור bechor
and מעשר ma'aser you pour on the base of the מזבח mizbe'ach
maybe one מתנה, matanah, the עולה olah you do all around. So
you don't know, so what you going to do? You can't bring
them. So why not do the two piles of money and sort
of separate out the תערובת, ta'arovet, you know, wherever the עולה olah
is is transferred here, wherever the בכור bechor is is transferred here?
Well, you can't do that because you can't redeem בכור bechor and
מעשר. ma'aser. So what can you do? So ירעו עד שיסתאבו, Yiru
ad sheyistavu, you let them graze until they get a מום, mum,
ויאכלו כבכור וכמעשר. Veye'akhlu kevochor ukhima'aser.
So now what you do
is you've got, you know, a בכור bechor and מעשר ma'aser with
a blemish, you know, can be eaten without bringing them as a
קרבן. korban. So
what you're going to do is, so there's a way even though
you cannot redeem them, there's a way that they don't go to
waste. Okay, in the case of the עולה olah and the שלמים,
shelamim, the only thing you could do with a שלמים shelamim is
redeem it and use the money to buy another שלמים. shelamim. Here
with the עולה olah and the בכור, bechor, there's going to be
no redeeming going on, okay, for the עולה. olah. For the בכור
Bechor or the מעשר, Maaser, but there will you can go ahead
and eat it. So it
says, יאכל כבכור וכמעשר. Yeiachel kebechor uchemaser. So what you do is
you say wherever the עולה Olah is it's, you know, it's redeemed
on this money. You take the $100 and you buy an עולה.
Olah. So the עולה Olah is going to be brought. Now that
they have a מום, Mum, you can redeem the עולה. Olah. So
there will be an עולה Olah brought. Now you have two animals
here: one is חולין Chulin and one is בכור Bechor or מעשר.
Maaser. They both have a מום. Mum. So you can eat בכור
Bechor and מעשר Maaser with a מום, Mum, and you can eat
חולין, Chulin, so go ahead and eat it. So what does it
mean that it is it is
eaten like בכור Bechor and מעשר? Maaser? Because בכור Bechor and מעשר,
Maaser, the הלכה Halacha is that in order that when you go
ahead and you're selling it, you cannot sell it in like the
butcher store in the marketplace because it's not considered respectful. Normally קדשים,
Kodshim, you redeem them, the קדושה Kedusha goes off, and then you
can sell it even in the butcher store and in the marketplace.
Also because that's how you'll get the best price and therefore you'll
redeem it on its full price, because you'll redeem it based on
the price that you would sell it for. But because a בכור,
Bechor, 'A', the קדושה Kedusha was never redeemed and removed, and 'B',
because you're not going to be redeeming it, so the price doesn't
matter, you're not allowed to go ahead and if you know and
go ahead and like
slaughter it in a marketplace, sell it in the marketplace, and so
on. So therefore because you have a בכור Bechor and חולין Chulin
mixed together now, you have to treat both of them as as
בכור Bechor and have this restriction apply.
Okay. הכל יכולים להתערב חוץ מן החטאת ואשם. Hakol yecholim lehitaarev chutz
min hachatas veasham. Any two types of things: חטאת, Chatas, עולה, Olah,
שלמים, Shelamim, etc. You can get scenarios where they could be mixed
together, except for חטאת Chatas and an אשם, Asham, because a חטאת
Chatas is female and an אשם Asham is male. So you'll never
get a scenario where those two will be mixed. Okay. That was
a pretty dense משנה. Mishna. Let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara.
Okay. And really of all the תוספותים, Tosafotim, there's really very little
to say. The big, big, big תוספות Tosafot is really going to
be relevant for tomorrow, so we'll worry about that tomorrow. All right,
so let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. מאי
אפילו? Mai afilu? What does it mean even, you know, one in
ten thousand? Because it sounds like ten thousand שור הנסקלים Shor Haniskalim
got mixed up with one קרבן, Korban, which is obviously that's a
problem. הכי קאמר. Hachi kaamar. No, here's what it means.
כל הזבחים שנתערבו בהן חטאת המתות או שור הנסקל. Kol hazvachim shenitarchu
bahen chatas hametos o shor haniskal. It's not that, you know, it's
that you have a flock of קדשים Kodshim that one חטאת המתה,
Chatas hameta, one or one שור הנסקל Shor haniskal got mixed up
in them. אפילו אחד בריבוא. Afilu echad berivo. So the one is
not going on the one קרבן, Korban, it's going on the one
forbidden animal: the חטאת Chatas that has to die or the שור
הנסקל, Shor haniskal, even one in ten thousand קרבנות, Korbanot, they all
have to they all have to die. ימותו כולן. Yamutu kulan. So
now the גמרא Gemara says: תנינא חדא זימנא. Tanina chada zimna. You
know, we have this idea that when animals get mixed up and
these things that are אסורין בהנאה Asurin behanaah get mixed up that
everything is forbidden. We have that in other משניות. Mishnayos. We teach
in תמורה: Temurah: כל האסורין לגבי מזבח, Kol haasurin legabei mizbeach, all
animals that can't be used for the מזבח, Mizbeach, for example, you
know,
a crossbreed, a Caesarean section, something that a שור הנסקל Shor haniskal
that there was only one witness etc., etc., that you can get
benefit from but can't be used for the
מזבח. Mizbeach. Okay. ואסורין בכל שהוא. Veasurin bechol shehu. If they get
mixed up with חולין, Chulin, it's not our case, not getting mixed
up with קדשים, Kodshim, they get mixed up with חולין, Chulin, then
you can't use any of the animals for the מזבח. Mizbeach. It
makes all of them forbidden. So essentially it's the same idea: one
gets mixed up with many, they're all forbidden.
הרובע והנרבע Harovea vehanirva and it starts giving the examples, animal, you
know, bestiality and so on. So אמר רב אשי: Amar Rav Ashi:
so why do you need to say it twice? רב אשי Rav
Ashi said: אמריתי לשמעתיה קמיה דרב שימי, Amritih lshmateih kamei d'Rav Shimi,
I said this discussion to רב שימי. Rav Shimi. וצריכא, Utzricha, and
רב שימי, Rav Shimi, he explained to me why each case was
necessary. דאי מהתם, De'i mehatam, had you just had the case in
תמורה, Temurah, where it was one of these things that are forbidden
to the מזבח Mizbeach getting mixed up in חולין. Chulin.
הוה אמינא, Hava amina, I would have thought to say, הני מילי
לגבוה אבל להדיוט אימא לא.
Hanei milei legavoah aval
l'hediot eima lo.
That's where you're telling me, it's not exactly clear what these phrases
mean, it's very turgid, but here's the point: that's when you're telling
me, okay, don't use any of these animals for a קרבן. Korban.
One of these got mixed up with חולין, Chulin, it's all חולין
Chulin right now, so it's forbidden to use for a קרבן. Korban.
That makes sense. You know, you shouldn't be using this stuff, go
make a better choice. Okay. אבל
להדיוט אימא לא, Aval l'hediot eima lo, but in our case, in
our משנה, Mishna, we're actually saying that when let's say the שור
הנסקל Shor Haniskal gets mixed up, we're actually saying that there's no
solution. You can't even redeem it and have a, you know, and
have a
layperson eat it. Because if you could redeem them and have a
layperson eat it, it wouldn't have said they have to all have
to die. Since it says they all have to die, it's... clear
that not only can you not bring it as a קרבן, korban,
but also even for a lay person, even after they're redeemed it's
a problem. So maybe I would have said, okay, when it gets
mixed up, don't use it for a קרבן, korban, okay, but I
wouldn't have said when it gets mixed up a lay person can't
eat it, maybe ביטול bitul will apply for a lay person. So
that's why it had to tell us here that it even for
a lay person it's forbidden, even though that's only implicit not explicit.
ואי מהא הכא, Ve'ee me'ha hacha, so why not just say it
here, our case? הוה אמינא הני מילי דאיסורי הנאה, Hava amina hanei
milei d'issurei hana'ah, because our משנה mishna that speaks about it being
forbidden to a lay person are things that are forbidden to lay
people, you know, the one problematic one, the שור הנסקל shor haniskal
for example, or you know, or the חטאת המתה, chatas hamesah, let's
say the שור הנסקל. shor haniskal. Okay, so a שור הנסקל shor
haniskal gets mixed up with a flock, it's forbidden בהנאה, be'hana'ah, it's
very, very weighty. It's not בטל. batel. You can't use them for
קרבנות korbanos and you can't even use it for a lay person.
That's essentially what our משנה mishna is saying. But maybe if it
was something that wasn't so weighty, it wasn't a שור הנסקל, shor
haniskal, it was only I don't know, a Caesarean section, maybe that
wouldn't make everything forbidden to be used for a קרבן? korban? אבל
הני
אימא לא, Aval hanei eima lo, but in the case of things
like that that don't make it are not איסורי הנאה, issurei hana'ah,
just forbidden for a קרבן, korban, maybe it doesn't make the whole
תערובת ta'aroves forbidden? צריכי, Tzrichi, so that's why you needed דלאו איסורי
הנאה נינהו. d'lav issurei hana'ah ninhu. So therefore it had to tell
you the case in תמורה Tmurah where the problematic thing was like
a C-section thing and therefore it was even though it wasn't איסורי
הנאה, issurei hana'ah, it gets mixed up and everything is forbidden to
be used as a קרבן. korban. Okay, so again, the first case
in our משנה mishna is איסורי הנאה issurei hana'ah gets mixed up
with קרבנות, korbanos, and therefore it can't be used for קרבן, korban,
can't be used for a הדיוט. hedyot. If it could be used
even for a lay person, then you would just redeem it. The
case in תמורה Tmurah is, I'll just call it C-section, things that
can't be used for קרבן korban but are totally כשר, kosher, gets
mixed up in חולין. chulin. Okay, so there it's not as weighty,
it's only a C-section, not as problematic, okay, maybe it would be
בטל, batel, more reason to say it's בטל. batel. On the other
hand, you know,
there it's to use for a קרבן, korban, more reason to be
strict. So you had to tell me that case, that even though,
you know, that even though
it's something not so weighty, it's only a C-section, it's still a
problem. And you had to tell us our case that, you know,
that it's forbidden even to a הדיוט. hedyot. So now the גמרא
Gemara says like this.
So the גמרא Gemara says,
or maybe I think I put the problem in the wrong place.
אימא לא צריכי, Eima lo tzrichi, period. Now the גמרא Gemara says
like this: דלאו איסורי הנאה נינהו תנא ליה, D'lav issurei hana'ah ninhu
tana lei, one minute, but that case of תמורה Tmurah is the
second part of our משנה. mishna. The first part of our משנה
mishna was שור הנסקל shor haniskal gets mixed up with a group,
okay, איסורי הנאה issurei hana'ah very weighty but can't even be used
for הדיוט. hedyot. But the next part of our משנה mishna is
very similar to the משנה mishna over there in תמורה. Tmurah. The
next part of our משנה mishna is C-section gets mixed up with
קרבנות. korbanos. You know, it's sort of the same as the משנה
mishna there. That משנה mishna there is C-section getting mixed up with
חולין. chulin. But the point is still the same: can't use it
for a קרבן, korban, can't use it for a הדיוט. hedyot. So
why do you need to tell me both cases?
So the גמרא Gemara says no, מכדי תני בכל שהוא או בכמה
כל שכן התם קתני. Michdi tani be'chol shehu o b'kama kol sheken
hatam katanei. No, here it doesn't say even one in ten thousand.
You know, it says it by the first part of the משנה,
mishna, not the second. But it's the משנה mishna in תמורה Tmurah
that says C-section that gets mixed up with חולין, chulin, even the
smallest amount, even one in ten thousand. So that's why it had
to repeat it over there, which is not really a great answer.
Then just say that phrase here. So let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says. וניתנייה בהא ולא בעי הך? Venisniyah be'ha velo ba'ei hach?
Okay, why not say that case in תמורה, Tmurah, why did we
need the second part of our משנה mishna about C-section getting mixed
up with קרבנות? korbanos? So the גמרא Gemara says, תקנתא איצטריכא ליה.
Takanata itztricha lei. So the גמרא Gemara says no, no, because what
you needed was our משנה mishna tells you how to fix it,
right? There are all, there are three separate cases. First case, איסורי
הנאה issurei hana'ah getting mixed up with קדשים. kodshim. Everything has to
die, which makes it implicit that it's אסור assur even for a
הדיוט. hedyot. Next case, in our case, in our משנה, mishna, C-section
gets mixed up with קדשים, kodshim, there's a way to fix it:
let it get a blemish, a מום, mum, redeem it, etc. Over
there, it's C-section gets mixed up with חולין, chulin, you can't bring
it as קרבן. korban. So the גמרא Gemara said we had to
tell us our case here, C-section with קדשים, kodshim, to tell us
how would you fix it. Over there it's not about fixing, C-section
with חולין, chulin, it's just don't use it for קרבן. korban. And
the reason we taught it over there was to add the phrase
אפילו אחד בריבוא אפילו כל שהוא. afillu echad b'ribbu afillu kol shehu.
Okay. I hope you followed all that. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this. דהדיוט נמי תנא ליה ואלו. D'hedyot nami tana
lei ve'elu. So one minute says the גמרא, Gemara, you know, we
had you said that the case of our משנה mishna was needed
about a שור הנסקל shor haniskal getting mixed up to tell you
it's forbidden even to a lay person. person that איסורי הנאה issurei
hana'ah that gets mixed up is forbidden even to a layperson that's
implicit in our משנה Mishnah that says you have to let them
all die there's no way to fix it to let a layperson
eat it. So the גמרא Gemara says well we know that already
that איסורי הנאה issurei hana'ah that gets mixed up is forbidden to
a layperson because we taught the following. This is a משנה. Mishnah.
ואלו אסורין ואוסרין בכל שהוא. ve'eilo asurin ve'osrin bechol shehu. The following
things are forbidden and forbidden even a smallest amount. יין נסך ועבודת
כוכבים. yein nesech va'avodas kochavim. Wine
of עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, an idol that was worshipped.
Now it's exactly a question what are the parameters. Our משנה's Mishnah
focusing on animals as being the key thing that's not בטל. batel.
There it's focusing on the idea that something that's איסורי הנאה issurei
hana'ah is not בטל. batel.
You know so we won't worry about that right now but let's
now just assume that the idea is איסורי הנאה's issurei hana'ah not
בטל. batel. So the גמרא Gemara says okay that's implicit in our
משנה Mishnah but it's already a principle that was taught over there
you know in עבודה זרה avodah zarah and elsewhere that איסורי הנאה
issurei hana'ah is not בטל. batel. So the גמרא Gemara says no
צריכי tzrichi you need both cases. Top of ע"א. ayin aleph amud
aleph. ואי מהתם הוה אמינא להדיוט אבל לגבוה אימא לא נפסדינהו לכולהו.
ve'ei mehatam havah amina lehedyot aval legavoah eima lo nafsidinhu lechulhu. If
it were there it'd say sure איסורי הנאה issurei hana'ah gets mixed
up then you know don't you a layperson benefit from it. But
maybe if it gets mixed up with קדשים kodashim maybe you know
on the one hand we have to be more protective of קדשים
kodashim so obviously you can't use it. But on the other hand
you could say no we don't want to throw out all these
קרבנות. korbanot. So therefore we're going to let ביטול bitul work by
the case of
קרבנות. korbanot. ואי מהכא הוה אמינא הני מילי קדשים דמאיס. ve'ei meihacha
havah amina hanei milei kodashim dema'is. That's because we want to be
more protective of קדשים. kodashim. Yes we have to throw out the
קרבנות korbanot but it would be disgusting to allow something to be
brought that might be עבודה זרה avodah zarah איסורי הנאה issurei hana'ah
whatever it might be. So אבל חולין דלא
מאיס אימא איסורי הנאה ליבטלו ברוב aval chullin delo ma'is eima issurei
hana'ah libatlu berov but for layperson that you know our standards aren't
as high so
maybe I should let it be בטל ברוב. batel berov. So therefore
it teaches צריכי tzrichi you need both cases. All right so basically
each one of these is different. Over there it said איסורי הנאה
issurei hana'ah is not בטל batel even for a layperson. Here it
says איסורי הנאה issurei hana'ah is not בטל batel for קדשים kodashim
and also implicitly for layperson or else you would be able to
redeem it. All right and we also see that things that are
not איסורי הנאה issurei hana'ah but animals or whatever if they can't
be used as a קרבן korban like C-section also gets mixed up
with חולין chullin gets mixed up with קרבנות. korbanot. Everything cannot be
used. So the basic principle though is nothing is בטל batel can't
be used and the גמרא Gemara will actually start then to ask
tomorrow well why doesn't ביטול bitul work? So for that tune in
tomorrow.